Guide to the Hudson River Day Line Records 1818-1949 MS 315
New-York Historical Society
Hudson River Day Line records
1818-1949
New-York Historical Society
Hudson River Day Line
MS 315
97 Linear feet in 45 record cartons, 375 bound volumes + 1 oversize folder
The collection includes the records of the Hudson River Day Line, spanning roughly the entire 100 year history (1840s-1940s) of the company and its predecessor and related entities. The Day Line is best recalled for its passenger service, carrying people for business or pleasure up and/or down the Hudson River between New York City and Albany, with various stops along the way, but its history reaches back to the mid-19th century and its steam towing operations. The collection includes financial and transaction records, correspondence, scrapbooks, publicity material, timetables, ephemera, ship-level records of passengers landed and received, and more. Much of the documents relate to specific steamboats, including the Alida, Anna, Armenia, Austin, Cayuga, Chauncey Vibbard, Commerce, E. Corning Jr., Daniel Drew, Mary Powell, Mercury, New York, Ontario, Oswego, Schuyler, Seneca, and others
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Although the collection is unprocessed, the bulk is accessible for use. There are some files that are in poor or fragile condition and require special advance arrangements with the curator of manuscripts before use; these are noted in the container list.
Arrangement
The collection is organized by format:
Series I. Files
Series II. Bound Volumes
Biographical / Historical
The Hudson River Day Line, which operated in various forms from the 1840s until 1949, is best recalled for its passenger service, carrying people for business or pleasure up and/or down the Hudson River between New York City and Albany, with various stops along the way. Its roots went back to the early 19th century and the shipping concerns of Abraham Van Santvoord (1784-1858). By the 1820s, Abraham had become the New York agent for the Steam Navigation Company, one of the first companies to operate steamboats for towing non-powered canal boats. In 1845, he was an organizer and first president of the Hudson River Steamboat Company. In 1848, Abraham had built the Oswego, the first of the large side-wheel steamers designed and built specifically for towing (this collection holds records from the Oswego).
Abraham's son, Alfred (1819-1901), joined the Hudson River Steamboat Company as its Albany agent, with his role in the organization expanding after his father's death. In 1855, Alfred bought the Alida, a day line (as opposed to a night line, with sleeping accommodations) passenger ship and began running regular service between New York and Albany. Over the following ten years, Alfred expanded his line of ships to include the Armenia, the Mary Powell, the Daniel Drew, and the Chauncey Vibbard, and perhaps others. Passenger travel for Alfred's company increased beginning in the 1860s, from 22,000 in 1863, to 173,000 in 1876 and to 192,000 in 1892.
The organization itself also evolved. Partners in the company at this time included John McBride Davidson and Chauncey Vibbard. Vibbard was also a superintendent of the New York Central Railroad, confirming the important business and transportation relationships between the railroads and steamships. In 1879, Alfred's New York and Albany Day Line incorporated, renaming itself formally as the Hudson River Line, though the Day Line reference remained in use. Its stock of ships also turned over, as the old ships Armenia and Daniel Drew were destroyed by fire (1886), the Vibbard was sold (1880s), and two steel hulled boats, the Albany (1880) and New York (1887), were constructed. In 1899, the Hudson River Line officially changed its corporate name to the Hudson River Day Line.
In 1901, Alfred Van Santvoord died of a stroke aboard his yacht, the Clermont. Alfred's son-in-law, Eben Erskine Olcott (1854-1929), took over as president of the Day Line, a position he held until his death. Olcott was the son of John Nathaniel Olcott and Euphemia Helen (Knox) Olcott. He had married Alfred's daughter, Katherine, in 1884 and, upon the death in 1895 of Alfred's only son, Olcott had become more heavily involved in the Day Line's management. Olcott had graduated in 1874 from the School of Mines at Columbia and retained his extensive mining interests, notably in Central and South America, into the 20th century. Under Olcott's leadership, the Day Line's ridership would surge from 266,000 in 1902 to almost 2 million in 1925. New ships were brought on line: Hendrick Hudson (1906), Robert Fulton (1909), Washington Irving (1909), De Witt Clinton (1921), Alexander Hamilton (1924), Chauncey M. Depew (1925), and Peter Stuyvesant (1925). Ships also were brought off-line: New York lost to fire, 1909; Mary Powell, retired in 1919; Albany, sold in 1934; and the Washington Irving, sank in 1926, with three deaths.
Eben Olcott died in 1929, and his son Alfred Van Santvoord Olcott (1886-1961), the donor of this collection, took over as President. But the Great Depression hurt the company financially and its business was scaled back. Into the 1940s, the emergence of automobiles and highways and other forms of recreation reduced the need for and interest in the Day Line, and it went out of business in 1949, selling its assets to other organizations. By that time four steamboats were still running: the Alexander Hamilton, Peter Stuyvesant, Hendrick Hudson, and Robert Fulton. A successor company, which is not part of this collection, continued to run a dwindling number of steamboats up the Hudson to Bear Mountain and West Point until 1971 when the last of them, the Alexander Hamilton, made a final voyage.
(The above note was based primarily on "A Short History of the Hudson River Day Line" by Peter Hess, found at https://www.newyorkalmanack.com/2017/02/a-short-history-of-the-hudson-river-day-line/. A biography of Eben Olcott can be found at https://prabook.com/web/eben.olcott/3763677.)
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection was a gift of Alfred V.S. Olcott, son of Eben E. Olcott and President of the Hudson River Day Line, donated over time from 1948-1951.
Scope and Contents
The collection includes the records of the Hudson River Day Line, spanning roughly the entire 100 year history (1840s-1940s) of the company and its predecessor and related entities. The collection includes financial and transaction records, towing records, correspondence, scrapbooks, publicity material, timetables, ephemera, ship-level records of passengers landed and received, and more. Much of the documents relate to specific steamboats, including the Alexander Hamilton, Alida, Anna, Armenia, Austin, Cayuga, Chauncey Vibbard, Commerce, E. Corning Jr., Daniel Drew, Hendrick Hudson, Mary Powell, Mercury, New York, Ontario, Oswego, Robert Fulton, Schuyler, Seneca, various barges, and others.
Related Materials
The Hudson River Day Line records are part of a larger body of materials donated in the 1940s-1950s by A.V.S. Olcott. Those donations were formed into at least three collections, including this one. Two other collections formed from the Olcott donations were:
Alfred Olcott collection of Hudson River Steamboats (PR 98). This collection focuses on photographs, blueprints, prints, and other graphic materials.
Eben Erskine Olcott papers. This collection includes papers related to Olcott's mining interests, education, and personal correspondence.
In addition, a search in Bobcat on "Hudson River Day Line" will identify several other resources, including some manuscript material.
Hudson-Fulton Celebration, 1909.; Hudson River (N.Y. and N.J.) -- Steam-navigation.; Passenger ships; River steamers -- Hudson River (N.Y. and N.J.); Steamboat lines -- Hudson River (N.Y. and N.J.); Steamboats -- Hudson River (N.Y. and N.J.).; Financial records.; Letters (correspondence); Printed ephemera.; Scrapbooks.; Shipping records.; Specifications.; Waybills.; Catskill and Tannersville Railroad; Catskill Mountain Railroad Corporation; Hudson River Day Line -- Archives.; Olcott, Eben (Eben Erskine); Van Santvoord, Alfred, 1819-1901
- Series I. Files, 1818-1949; 45 Linear feet
  Scope and Contents
  The series includes a broad range of documents including ephemera (postcards, tickets, publicity brochures, timetables, etc.); booklets (on-board magazines, trip/excursion descriptions, guide books, etc.); tariff/fare schedules; way bills of tickets collected (i.e., packets by steamer for each day recording the number of passengers by port along the route and other details); steamer inspection certificates; insurance policies; annual reports; subject files concerning railroads in the Catskills, the steamboats Alexander Hamilton and De Witt Clinton, and the Hudson-Fulton Celebration and replica Clermont; the capital stock register book for the Mary Powell Steamship Company; a report on the sinking of the Washington Irving; miscellaneous financial documents; and other documents. The container list provides some further details, though the description is based on a broad survey of the content of the boxes.
  Arrangement
  The series is arranged roughly by format/subject matter.
  - Postcards; Tickets; Library records, 1860s-1940s, undated (Offsite-box 1)
    1) Includes many postcards, including many duplicates, generally undated. 2) Includes tickets and other stubs, 1860s-1940s. Most of the tickets and passes are undated, but a few indicate they are from the 1860s; many are single tickets or sheets stamped "sample" and are dated from the 1930s-1940s. There are a variety of tickets, including those for on/off on various stops, meal tickets, luggage tags, etc. 3) Includes index cards noting the reading material available on board, and a Hudson River Day Line Library rubber stamp (1920s?).
  - Brochures, placards, and other publicity/advertising (22 folders), 1890s-1949 (Offsite-box 2)
    Includes a set of 12 envelopes of publicity material as originally donated, chronologically arranged from 1937-1948. Another 10 folders includes compiled materials dating from the 1890s to the 1940s, with most dating from the 1910s. Includes posters/placards of schedules (1910s); some menus, including one for a dinner to Mrs. Wilton Merle-Smith on the Washington Irving (1913); sheet music for "On the Hudson River (Day Line Moonlight Sail)" (1948); two punch-out paper models of the Hendrick Hudson (unassembled, in original envelope for mailing); and the advertisement from Indian Point Corporation (formerly Hudson River Day Line) for the liquidation auction of six properties (1949). Some material is not specifically that of the Day Line, though it relates to their business; most notable of these is a plan of the floors of the Hotel Champlain at Bluff Point, Lake Champlain (undated).
  - Steamship "Mary Powell" (8 folders), 1869-1918 (Offsite-box 2)
    Includes 24 annual guides from the Mary Powell, 1888-1913 (missing 1891, 1895, 1903, 1904); a 1918 memorial book; passes for years 1886-1914 (some gaps); bill of sale for the Mary Powell to Alfred Van Sanvoort and J. McB. Davidson (1869); and the capital stock ownership register for the Mary Powell Steamship Company (1899-1902).
  - Publicity and other printed material, 1850-1948 (Offsite-box 3)
    Includes a broad range of printed material, including timetables, schedules, guide maps, trip descriptions, tourist maps (including an 1850 map), souvenir booklets, commemorative booklets, some Day Line Magazines (1910s), and a copy of the Day Line Rules & Regulations for its employees (1927). Includes materials specifically about the river trips, but also related places, such as Bear Mountain State Park.
  - Pamphlets, magazines and other promotional materials, circa 1918-1940s (Offsite-box 4)
    Includes an orderly set of original files of printed publicity material, in chronological order circa 1918-1940s
  - Files re: Hudson-Fulton celebration (11 folders), 1902-1909 (Offsite-box 5)
    Includes correspondence of Eben Olcott, among other documents. Some specific subjects include the replica Clermont (specifications, the record of its voyage, and bill of sale to the Day Line (1909); and materials concerning planning for the Hudson Tri-Centennial Memorial Bridge (also referred to as the Hendrick Hudson Bridge) over the Harlem Ship Canal at Spuyten Duyvil.
  - Photograph of Hendrick Hudson statue sculpted by J. Massey Rhind (oversize), undated (Box OS-Medium)
    Item found in stacks, 2022. Unframed by conservator Alan Balicki and added to collection by archivist Larry Weimer, September 2022.
  - Files on various subjects (11 folders), 1818-1935 (Offsite-box 5)
    Includes various documents not necessarily related to the Day Line:
    * Letters (1818-1860s), including two from Euphemia Knox (Eben Olcott's mother), and perhaps two to her including one from Jacob Van Vechten concerning the Civil War (1864)
    * special order (1864) from George Monroe of the 22nd Kentucky Volunteers
    * invoice related to improving Hudson River navigation at New Baltimore (1867)
    * various invitations, including some specifically to Eben Olcott (1925-1926)
    * deed of sale of New York property from Euphemia M. Olcott to Eben Olcott (1889)
    * Alfred Van Santvoord memorial book from United New Jersey Railroad and Canal Company (1901)
    * signed petition to the U.S. Congress for a Highlands of the Hudson River National Park (undated)
    * a typed manuscript "A Tete-a-Tete Driving Trip," written by Kate H. Huntington and describing her travels in the Berkshires (1906)
    * annotated programme of the Ecumenical Conference on Foreign Mission (1900), with newspaper accounts (in poor condition)
    * Official's ribbon for the Indian Point Outboard Motorboat Regatta (1935)
    * 5 photographs (George Washington Blauvelt; Timothy H. Roberts of Flatbush; Pilgrim Mother statue; and two of the damaged depot of the Peoples Line of the Hudson Navigation Company (1913)
    * an insurer's report on the sinking of the steamship Washington Irving (1926)
    * and documents concerning a dispute between the Harlem Company and the New York and Harlem Railroad Company (1898).
  - Hudson River Day Line annual financial reports, 1879-1948 (Offsite-box 5)
    Specific years in the file are: 1879-1890, 1927, 1930, 1932-1948. Other years are not here. Also two blank, small ledger booklets.
  - Legal documents (1 folder), 1850s-1929 (Offsite-box 6)
    Charter of the Peoples Line/New Jersey Steamboat Company (1854); several bills of sale for vessels, including barges, River Queen, Seneca, New York, and several bought from the special master for the Central Hudson Steamboat Company (1929); and charter party agreement for the River Queen (1888).
  - Specifications; Certificates of inspection (12 folders), 1879, 1906-1940s (Offsite-box 6)
    Specifications: 1) hull of an iron side-wheeled steamer (Albany), 1879; 2) hull, carpenter and joiner work for side wheel steamboat for Albany Day Line (i.e., Robert Fulton), 1908; 3) hull, carpenter work & boiler for paddle wheel steamboat, 1911; 4) paddle wheel steamers, 1922 and 1925 (steel); 5) electric lighting, plumbing, heating, ventilation for Washington Irving; and 6) steel freight steamer (1922). Certificates of inspection (1930s-1940s): Alexander Hamilton, Robert Fulton, Peter Stuyvesant, Hendrick Hudson, Chauncey M. Depew, De Witt Clinton, and various barges. Certificate of enrollment for Hendrick Hudson (1906).
  - Various financial transaction records (9 folders, 7 small volumes), 1834-1920s (Offsite-box 6)
    These files are largely unarranged documents regarding various transactions. Bulk is from 1850s-1890s. There are many invoices, receipts/vouchers (earliest is 1834), journal/ledger sheets, expense lists (including repairs and alterations, such as for the Albany, Armenia, and Cayuga), unpaid bills (e.g. Cayuga), and other detailed financial data often relating to specific ships. A few financial documents reference the Swiftsure Line. There are some letters and specifications related to ship alterations, such as proposals from the North River Iron Works. A folder of documents relates to an inquiry of Eben Olcott regarding light draft steamboats, with correspondence, a blueprint, 5 photographs from Yarrow & Co of London, etc. There are also some indentures and insurance policies (Clermont, Mary Powell and Armenia) in these files, and a record of insurance policies (1864). Some material relates to other companies, including financial data for the Delaware & Otsego Railroad Company (1892) and the Ulster & Delaware Railroad (1893). There are sheets of blank towing receipts for Van Santvoord's Line, the Hudson River Steamboat Co., and a generic form. The small volumes include steamship transactions of the 1860s-1870s; steamer New York inventories (1894) and repairs and furnishings; and William Mackay's New York inventory for 1868-69.
  - Unpaid bills, financial records, rate schedules and clippings, 1850s-1860s, 1915-1948 (Offsite-box 7)
    Includes unpaid bills lists from 1850s-1860s; a classification of expenses for the SS Chauncey Vibbard, 1867; letterpress copybook of General Ticket Agent C.R. van Benthuysen, 1883-1887; adoption notice re: the Mary Powell (1915); tariff/fare rates (passengers, charters, etc.) for circa 1923-1948; and some clippings (1940).
  - Passenger reports, 1927-1941 (Offsite-box 8)
    Statistical reports of numbers of passengers by pick-up points/ports and date
  - Local and joint passenger tariff, 1900-1928 (Offsite-box 9)
    Orderly files of printed material with annual fares.
  - Newspapers (1 of 2), circa 1870s-1900s (Offsite-box 10)
    Includes unorganized, folded newspapers in fragile condition. Advance arrangements for use of these materials must be made with the curator of manuscripts.
  - Newspapers (2 of 2), circa 1870s-1900s (Offsite-box 11)
    See note for box 10.
  - Way bills, 1863-1899 (Offsite-box 12)
    This box includes an inventory prepared in 1919 of the waybills from the 1860s-1908 preserved by the Day Line, now found in this box and the next (boxes 12 and 13). The note indicates that all other waybills were destroyed in 1919, which would account for the gap in the collection of waybills between 1908 and 1916. According to that list this box holds waybills from the following steamboats: Daniel Drew (1863-1880), Armenia (1863-1878), Chauncey Vibbard(1864-1886), Albany(1880-1899), and New York (1887-1899).
  - Way bills, 1900-1908 (Offsite-box 13)
    See the note for box 12. According to the referenced inventory, this box holds waybills from the following steamboats: Albany (1900-1908), New York (1900-1908), Mary Powell (1903-1908), and Hendrick Hudson 1906-1908).
  - Way bills, 1916-1922 (Offsite-box 14)
  - Way bills, 1937 (Offsite-box 15)
  - Way bills, 1937 (Offsite-box 16)
  - Way bills, 1939 (Offsite-box 17)
  - Way bills, 1939 (Offsite-box 18)
  - Way bills, 1940 (Offsite-box 19)
  - Way bills, 1940 (Offsite-box 20)
  - Way bills, 1941 (Offsite-box 21)
  - Way bills, 1941 (Offsite-box 22)
  - Way bills, 1942 (Offsite-box 23)
  - Way bills, 1942 (Offsite-box 24)
  - Way bills, 1943 (Offsite-box 25)
  - Way bills, 1943 (Offsite-box 26)
  - Way bills, 1944 (Offsite-box 27)
  - Way bills, 1944 (Offsite-box 28)
  - Way bills, 1945 (Offsite-box 29)
  - Way bills, 1945 (Offsite-box 30)
  - Way bills, 1946 (Offsite-box 31)
  - Way bills, 1946 (Offsite-box 32)
  - Way bills, 1947 (Offsite-box 33)
  - Way bills, 1947 (Offsite-box 34)
  - Way bills, 1948 (Offsite-box 35)
  - Way bills, 1948 (Offsite-box 36)
  - Files re: Steamship De Witt Clinton, 1920-1921 (Offsite-box 37)
    Contents all relate to the addition of the De Witt Clinton (ex-Nopatin, ex-Manhattan) to the line. Topics include purchase of the ship from the Navy, furnishings (includes fabric samples), trial run, inspection, research for publicity and other purposes, etc.
  - Files re: Steamship Alexander Hamilton, 1923-1924 (Offsite-box 38)
    Includes several files on the construction, furnishing (including fabric samples), inspection, etc., of the ship.
  - Files re: Other steamship lines, 1933-1934 (Offsite-box 38)
    About 60 folders labeled with a name of a steamship line (some railroad companies), generally each with a single sheet of paper listing the ships of that company with basic descriptive details of each ship. Appears to be basic information for competitive comparison purposes. The companies generally appear to be from New York State and New England.
  - Hudson River Day Line annual reports submitted to the Interstate Commerce Commission (ICC), 1914-1942 (Offsite-box 39)
    A set of 29 reports for years 1914-1942.
  - Files re: Catskill Mountain railroads, circa 1880-1914 (Offsite-box 40)
    Entire box includes legal documents, financial records, correspondence, and other documents concerning the Catskill Mountain Railway, the Catskill & Tannerville Railway, the Otis Elevating Railway, and the Otis Railway Company. The papers are mostly unorganized and loose.
  - Stewards' accounts, financial records (1 of 3), circa 1848-1860s (Offsite-box 41)
    3 boxes of steward accounts (provisions, supplies for ships); vouchers; cancelled checks; towing records; some correspondence. The documents are tri-folded with related documents bundled together. Many are brittle with water damage. Because of their condition, special arrangements must be made in advance of their use with the curator of manuscripts.
  - Stewards' accounts, financial records (2 of 3), circa 1848-1860s (Offsite-box 42)
    See note for box 41
  - Stewards' accounts, financial records (3 of 3), circa 1848-1860s (Offsite-box 43)
  - Printed material: Hudson River by Daylight, 1890-1900 (Offsite-box 44)
    Missing 1892
  - Printed material: Hudson River by Daylight, souvenir magazine, 1901-circa 1917 (Offsite-box 45)
- Series II. Bound Volumes, circa 1833-1948; 52 Linear feet (375 bound volumes)
  The series includes 375 bound and shelved volumes. Most of these are financial and transactional in nature ranging from the 1830s into the early 20th century, including captain's returns (cash collected by steamboat captains and turned over to the company agent), ledgers, cash books, journals, expense/revenue recapitulations, check books, outstanding (unpaid) bills, towing bills, bills of lading, and the like. There are several volumes of reports of passengers "landed and received," primarily from the 20th century. There are many volumes of letter books and letterpress copybooks. There are also various scrapbooks of clippings and of publicity material.
  The container list includes an inventory of all volumes. However, when the inventory was taken, all volumes had been shrinkwrapped for off-site storage. Consequently, for the most part the inventory is not based on a review of the volume content but was based on any labeling visible on the spines, inventories taken at the time of donation, inferences, and other observations short of unwrapping all but a few of the volumes. Inaccuracies, especially in date ranges, are likely. The absence of a date range in the container list means that no dates were observed on the exterior of the shrinkwrapped volume.
  In 2020, in preparing the bound volumes of the collection for off-site storage, each volume was given a sequence number (SN), which simply indicated the order of the volumes as found on the shelves. This finding aid presents the volumes in that same order, with reference to the sequence number. Related volumes were often found together on the shelves, but there was also a considerable degree of randomness that is reflected in the container list.
  - SS Alida. Captain's returns, 1867 (Offsite-box HR-1, Volume SN-1)
  - SS Alida. Captain's returns, 1862 (Offsite-box HR-1, Volume SN-2)
  - SS Alida. Captain's returns, 1857 (Offsite-box HR-1, Volume SN-3)